Akbar: … Very far, for the first time.
Akbar: İlk kez, çok uzaktaydı.
And I knew when he phoned that they found it out.
Ve o aradığında, bunu öğrendiklerini anladım.
[Unclear]
[Belirsiz]
Shri Mataji: You know because I asked her, “What is the temperature? Just find out.
Shri Mataji: Biliyorsunuz, çünkü ona sordum, "Sıcaklık kaç derece diye? Bir bakın.
Because I just really got shocked”.
Çünkü gerçekten çok şaşırdım."
We saw all the people very nicely going about without much on them.
Herkesin üzerinde pek bir şey olmadan çok güzel bir şekilde dolaştığını gördük.
[Laughter]
[Kahkaha]
Hello!
Merhaba!
Lady: What would you like to drink?
Bayan: Ne içmek istersiniz?
Shri Mataji: I mean, something cold: Coca Cola?
Shri Mataji: Soğuk bir şey: Coca Cola?
Lady: Coca Cola?
Bayan: Coca Cola mı?
Akbar: This is Yilmaz [unsure], Shri Mataji, he’s an engineer, mechanical engineer,
Akbar: Bu Yılmaz [emin değil], Shri Mataji, o bir mühendis, kendisi makine mühendisi.
Lady: This is cherry juice, OK?
Bayan: Bu vişne suyu, tamam mı?
Shri Mataji: May God bless you.
Shri Mataji: Tanrı sizleri korusun.
Man:
Adam:Nasılsınız?
Shri Mataji: I’m so happy to come here to meet you all.
Shri Mataji: Buraya gelip hepinizle tanıştığım için çok mutluyum.
Man: Nice to meet you.
Adam: Tanıştığımıza memnun oldum.
Shri Mataji: I was so anxious to meet you.
Shri Mataji: Sizinle tanışmak için çok sabırsızlanıyordum.
Akbar: Another great Sahaja Yogi in Islam.
Akbar: İslam'da bir başka harika Sahaja Yogi.
Shri Mataji: Really?
Shri Mataji: Gerçekten mi?
Akbar: This is Nowal, another engineer, mechanical engineer,
Akbar: Bu Nowal, bir başka mühendis, makine mühendisi.
Shri Mataji: Oh, I see. God has given the engineers here,
Shri Mataji: Anlıyorum. Tanrı buraya mühendisleri göndermiş,
engineers, you see, God’s ways.
mühendisler, görüyorsunuz, Tanrı'nın yolları.
Man: No Economist. Economist.
Adam: Hayır, ekonomist. Ekonomist.
Shri Mataji: Great.
Shri Mataji: Harika.
Economic. Architect?
Ekonomist. Mimar?
Man: Economist.
Adam: Ekonomist.
Shri Mataji: Economist. Ah, economist.
Shri Mataji: Ekonomist. Ah, ekonomist.
Hello, how are you?
Merhaba, nasılsınız?
Man: Fine thank you. And you?
Adam: İyiyim, teşekkürler. Ya siz?
Shri Mataji: May God bless you.
Shri Mataji: Tanrı sizi korusun.
So, she’s here for us. Good.
Demek bizim için buraya geldi. Güzel.
Beautiful flowers.
Güzel çiçekler.
It’s all right, it’s all right.
Sorun yok, sorun yok.
She doesn’t want to give because maybe of the horns.
O vermek istemiyor ... belki dikenler yüzünden.
[Cut in the video]
[Videoda kesinti]
Akbar: Mary is the wife of a doctor.
Akbar: Mary, bir doktorun karısı.
She couldn’t come because she said- the husband said that she had three patients,
Gelemedi çünkü kocası, üç hastası olduğunu,
she has to cure their teeth, so she couldn’t come.
Onların dişlerini tedavi etmesi gerektiğini söyledi, bu yüzden gelemedi.
Shri Mataji: [Laughter]
Shri Mataji: [Gülüşmeler]
Akbar: Her husband. She couldn’t come.
Akbar: Kocası. Gelemedi.
This is Serine,
Bu Serin,
it’s the first time she sees you.
sizi ilk kez görüyor.
Shri Mataji: First time.
Shri Mataji: İlk kez.
Serine: Can I kiss you?
Serin: Sizi öpebilir miyim?
Shri Mataji: Please.
Shri Mataji: Lütfen.
First time I see her. So, this is too much for me.
Onu ilk kez görüyorum. Yani, bu benim için çok fazla.
I am so happy we have so many people here.
Burada bu kadar çok insan olduğu için çok mutluyum.
Akbar: This is the Iranian, the first, the mother of Anik.
Akbar: Bu İranlı, ilk, Anik'in annesi.
She is the first people know. She has started Sahaja Yoga.
O, insanların tanıdığı ilk kişi. Sahaja Yoga'ya başladı.
She has got five students. She says.
Beş öğrencisi var. Öyle diyor.
Shri Mataji: Oh, in Iran?
Shri Mataji: Oh, İran'da mı?
Akbar: Iran.
Akbar: İran.
Shri Mataji: Iran is the first country I visited. Did you tell her?
Shri Mataji: İran, ziyaret ettiğim ilk ülke. Siz ona söylediniz mi?
Akbar: Yes, yes.
Akbar: Evet, evet.
Shri Mataji:
Shri Mataji: Hepinizi burada görmek çok güzel, çok güzel.
So nice to see you all here, so nice. It’s tremendous.
Bu muazzam.
I didn’t know this country had some potential, really.
Bu ülkenin potansiyeli olduğunu bilmiyordum, gerçekten.
Akbar: There are a lot more, they are outside.
Akbar: Dışarıda daha çok kişi var.
Lady:
Bayan: Sizi tekrar gördüğüme çok sevindim.
Shri Mataji: I come also for this task. And his mother, isn’t she?
Shri Mataji: Ben de bu görev için geldim. Ve annesi, değil mi?
Lady: And his mother.
Bayan: Ve annesi.
Shri Mataji: I talked to you on the phone once, remember?
Shri Mataji: Sizinle bir kez telefonda konuşmuştum, hatırladınız mı?
Sahaja Yogini:
Sahaja Yogini: Evet, evet, evet.
Shri Mataji: She’s so anxious.
Shri Mataji: Çok endişeli.
Akbar: She is, yes.
Akbar: Evet, öyle.
Sahaja Yogini: She’s from Strasbourg, there, Mother.
Sahaja Yogini: O, Strasbourg'dan, Anne.
Shri Mataji: From where?
Shri Mataji: Nereden?
Sahaja Yogini: From Strasbourg.
Sahaja Yogini: Strasbourg'dan.
Shri Mataji: Oh, Strasbourg. You are from Strasbourg?
Shri Mataji: Oh, Strasbourg. Siz Strasbourg'dan mısınız?
Sahaja Yogi: She is the wife of a doctor who is also a Sahaja Yogi, this lady.
Sahaja Yogi: O, aynı zamanda Sahaja Yogi olan bir doktorun karısı, bu hanımefendi.
Shri Mataji: So nice to see, being such,
Shri Mataji: Böyle harika birini
wonderful. It’s very tied,
görmek çok güzel. Çok sıkışık,
thank you.
teşekkürler.
Please be seated, all of you please be
Lütfen oturun, hepiniz oturun lütfen.
seated. Yes, thank you.
Evet, teşekkürler.
You are so close to, Turkey is so close to India.
Türkiye, Hindistan'a çok yakın.
And you had Kamel Pasha here. Long time back.
Ve burada Kemal Paşa vardı. Uzun zaman önce.
I always used to read his life and his ideas and things.
Onun hayatını, fikirlerini ve diğer şeylerini hep okurdum.
Sahaja Yogi: We are really blessed. It’s the second time in Turkey.
Sahaja Yogi: Gerçekten çok şanslıyız. Türkiye'ye ikinci kez geliyorum.
Perhaps you were more in Turkey only. Is that the second time?
Belki de sadece Türkiye'ye daha çok geldiniz. Bu ikinci kez mi?
Sahaja Yogi: Hello
Sahaja Yogi: Merhaba
Shri Mataji: Ah, hello!
Shri Mataji: Ah, merhaba!
What about Ruslan, he is not coming?
Ruslar ne olacak, gelmeyecekler mi?
Sahaja Yogi: I don’t know, I don’t think so.
Sahaja Yogi: Bilmiyorum, sanmıyorum.
Shri Mataji: I see. We should have telephone to him really.
Shri Mataji: Anlıyorum. Onları gerçekten telefonla aramalıyız.
He’s so close here.
Buraya çok yakın.
He’s Oman, he’s in Oman.
Oman'da, Oman'da.
It’s a very traditional country, that is, I have seen where ever there has been tradition,
Çok geleneksel bir ülke, yani, geleneklerin olduğu her yerde,
they have been able to see this evolution process.
bu evrim sürecini görebildiklerini gördüm.
But without a traditional country, it is very difficult to handle.
Ama geleneksel olmadan, bir ülke, bu çok zor.
You cannot understand.
Anlayamazsınız.
I don’t know, the Russian is not very good with the relationship with Turkey, Russians.
Bilmiyorum, Ruslar Türkiye ile ilişkilerinde pek iyi değiller.
Sahaja Yogini: Bad relations. They are just-
Sahaja Yogini: Kötü ilişkiler. Onlar sadece...
Shri Mataji: But there was a problem of people who were forces to come
Shri Mataji: Ama bir sorun vardı ... zorla getirilen insanlar
or something.
falan vardı.
Sahaja Yogi: In Greece.
Sahaja Yogi: Yunanistan'da.
Shri Mataji: OK.
Shri Mataji: Tamam.
But surprisingly,
Ama şaşırtıcı bir şekilde,
it’s very surprising, in Russia, thousands went on
çok şaşırtıcı, Rusya'da binlerce kişi gitti
and all very well-educated professionals, writers, it’s so amazing.
ve hepsi çok iyi eğitimli profesyoneller, yazarlar, bu çok şaşırtıcı.
I think they had no other freedom. So, they developed within themselves.
Sanırım başka özgürlükleri yoktu. Bu yüzden kendi içlerinde geliştiler.
People are so wonderful, very nice people.
İnsanlar çok harika, çok iyi insanlar.
And this problem is also created not by the government, anything,
Ve bu sorun da hükümet tarafından değil,
but by some bureaucrats who do not want to have this freedom business.
bu özgürlük işini istemeyen bazı bürokratlar tarafından yaratılıyor.
That’s why they are doing all this, not to give them food in this manner.
Bu yüzden tüm bunları yapıyorlar, onlara bu şekilde yemek vermek istemiyorlar.
But the people they say, “We don’t want any food. We don’t want anything.
Ama insanlar diyor ki, "Yemek istemiyoruz. Hiçbir şey istemiyoruz.
What we want is this liberation of the Spirit”. So well read, such nice people.
İstediğimiz şey Ruh'un özgürlüğü. Çok bilgili, çok iyi insanlar.
And there would be 2,000 people sitting inside the hall
Salonun içinde 2.000 kişi,
and 2,000 outside. [Laughter]
dışında da 2.000 kişi oturuyordu. Kahkahalar]
When I came up they would say, “Mother, we” they had to get some tickets to come to that hall.
Ben geldiğimde, Anne, biz..." diyorlardı, o salona girmek için bilet almaları gerekiyordu.
“There are no seats, we could not come, we could not hear you”.
"Koltuk yok, gelemedik, sizleri duyamadık." dediler.
I said, “All right, then what should we do? Can you come tomorrow morning?”
"Peki, o zaman ne yapmalıyız? Yarın sabah gelebilir misiniz?"
“Yes, we’ll come”. It was raining all of them were there next day,
"Evet, geliriz." dediler. Ertesi gün yağmur yağıyordu,
and we had a session just outside the hall.
ama hepsi oradaydı ve salonun hemen dışında bir seans yaptık.
And even now follow on is like that, in thousands. Nothing is less than thousand.
Ve şimdi bile binlerce kişi bu şekilde devam ediyor. Bin kişiden daha azı yok.
But they settled down and it’s very remarkable how they take to it so easily.
Ama onlar bunda yerleştiler ve bunu bu kadar kolay kabul etmeleri çok dikkat çekici.
And they have had all kinds of things, you know, Hatha Yoga, this fellow, that fellow,
Ve her türlü şeyi denediler, bilirsiniz, Hatha Yoga, şu adam, bu adam,
Yoganand, Karmananda, everything has been taken.
Yoganand, Karmananda, her şeyi denediler.
But they understand the reality so well!
Ama gerçeği çok iyi anlıyorlar!
Sahaja Yogini: They haven’t been spoiled by the Western culture.
Sahaja Yogini: Batı kültürü tarafından bozulmamışlar.
Shri Mataji: I just don’t know. This is a kind of a very deep
Shri Mataji: Bilmiyorum.
understanding what should be the truth.
Bu, gerçeğin ne olması gerektiğine dair çok derin bir anlayış.
It is a very deep understanding. I mean no problem of any kind.
Çok derin bir anlayış. Yani hiçbir sorun yok.
The government has accepted, the government has accepted us
Hükümet kabul etti, hükümet bizi
as an independent organization, only we!
bağımsız bir organizasyon olarak kabul etti, sadece bizi!
Otherwise, any other yoga, anything else, is in a combined way.
Aksi takdirde, diğer tüm yogalar, diğer her şey, birleşik bir şekilde.
But for us, they have given an independent way.
Ama bize bağımsız bir yol verdiler.
And now, one of the Ministers is coming
Ve şimdi, bakanlardan biri
for Ganapatipule. [Laughter]
Ganapatipule'ye geliyor. [Gülüşmeler]
He belongs to the Council of [unclear] the topmost
O, [belirsiz] en üst düzey
thing. He
konseyin bir üyesi.
is going to come.
O da gelecek.
They have no conditioning, I think, except for one.
Sanırım, bir tanesi hariç, Hiçbir şartlanma yok.
And they don’t- I mean they just say that, “We just want liberation of the Spirit”.
Ve onlar... Yani, sadece "biz sadece Ruhun kurtuluşunu istiyoruz" diyorlar.
No other conditionings.
Başka hiçbir koşullama yok.
And they’re not materialist,
Ve onlar materyalist değiller,
because they have never had all these nonsensical things that we had.
çünkü bizim sahip olduğumuz tüm bu saçma sapan şeylere hiç sahip olmadılar.
They have one problem, their [unclear], they do not work out outside.
Tek bir sorunları var, onların [belirsiz], dışarıda çalışmıyorlar.
That’s the only problem they have. Otherwise, so generous.
Tek sorunları bu. Aksi takdirde, çok cömertler.
Even in the hotel, the people, the maids, everybody is anxious to just touch my shawl.
Otelde bile, insanlar, hizmetçiler, herkes şalımla dokunmak için can atıyor.
I’ve been thinking, “What idea of spirituality they have?”
Düşündüm de, "Onların maneviyat anlayışı nedir?" diye.
of any kind.
Zaten hiçbir dinleri yoktu.
Christianity also it’s just like that, hanging.
Hristiyanlık da öyle, ortada kalmış durumda.
Also, some Muslims are there in this area of this Tashkent, Samarkar and these things.
Ayrıca, Taşkent, Semerkant ve bu tür yerlerde bazı Müslümanlar da var.
But I think there’s no conditioning of any kind there.
Ama bence orada hiçbir türden şartlanma yok.
Just they are waiting for the spirituality.
Sadece maneviyatı bekliyorlar.
And the right time now, Gorbachev has opened the doors
Ve şimdi doğru zaman. Gorbaçov kapıları açtı
and we were 40 people, first time we went, 40 people.
ve biz 40 kişiydik, ilk gittiğimizde 40 kişiydik.
And the way they looked after us! We didn’t pay a
Ve bize nasıl da baktılar!
single pie, 40 of us, we did not pay.
Tek kuruş bile ödemedik, 40 kişi, hiçbir şey ödemedik.
So full of devotion. That means, you see,
Çok adanmışlardı.
that Sahaja Yoga will be now nicely established.
Bu, Sahaja Yoga'nın artık güzel bir şekilde yerleşeceği anlamına geliyor.
Because according to one of the predictions of
Çünkü Bhrigumuni'nin
Bhrigumuni, in his book Nadi Granth,
Nadi Granth kitabındaki öngörülerinden birine göre,
he says that, “One super
"Bir süper güç Sahaja Yoga'yı benimseyecek" diyor.
power will take to Sahaja Yoga”. This is one of the super powers.
Bu süper güçlerden biri.
And then the Sahaja Yoga, in 1990, will be so established
Ve sonra Sahaja Yoga, 1990'da o kadar yerleşik hale gelecek ki,
that they will have to have a conference of people from all over the world
dünyanın her yerinden insanlar bir konferans düzenlemek zorunda kalacaklar
and they will be made in charge of the whole world.
ve onlar tüm dünyadan sorumlu olacaklar.
They have used ‘Sahaja’ word in that. I’ve got a beautiful booklet.
Orada "Sahaja" kelimesini kullanmışlar. Çok güzel bir kitapçığım var.
You’ve got the green booklet where is it?
Yeşil kitapçığın nerede?
Sahaja Yogini: In your luggage.
Sahaja Yogini: Valizinizde.
Shri Mataji: Hum?
Shri Mataji: Ha?
Shri Mataji: OK. In which somebody has also seen into Quran,
Shri Mataji: Tamam. Kuran'da da
the word Sahaja Yoga is there.
Sahaja Yoga kelimesi geçiyor.
Sahaja Yogini: Oh, yes.
Sahaja Yogini: Evet, doğru.
Shri Mataji: G. S.
Shri Mataji: G. S.
Sahaja Yogini: Y. S .
Sahaja Yogini: Y. S.
Shri Mataji: Y. S .
Shri Mataji: Y. S.
Sahaja Yogini: Cause it’s written there.
Sahaja Yogini: Çünkü orada yazıyor.
Shri Mataji: You see, Y suggests ‘yoga’.
Siz, gördün mü, Y "yoga"yı ima ediyor.
So, he’s given me that booklet. You have a look at it.
O Bana o kitapçığı verdi. Bir bak.
Sahaja Yogi: My name
Sahaja Yogi: Benim adım da Y.S.
Shri Mataji: Y.S. Really?
Shri Mataji: Y.S. Gerçekten mi?
Sahaja Yogi: Ylman Salman.Y. S.
Sahaja Yogi: Yılmaz Salman. Y. S.
Shri Mataji: Y. S. Ylmas?
Shri Mataji: Y. S. Yılmaz mı?
Sahaja Yogini: Ylman Salman. Salman.
Sahaja Yogini: Yılmaz Salman. Salman.
Shri Mataji: Means Salam, is it?
Shri Mataji: Salma anlamına mı geliyor?
Sahaja Yogini: Maybe.
Sahaja Yogini: Belki.
Shri Mataji: [Unclear].
Shri Mataji: [Anlaşılmıyor].
You know, I was sure Muhamad sahib would have written everything definitely,
Siz biliyorsunuz, Muhammad sahib'in her şeyi kesin olarak yazmış olacağından emindim,
because he’s one of the latest ones, he must have talked about it.
çünkü o en son gelenlerden biri, bunun hakkında konuşmuş olmalı.
Also, he said, “Until the Qiyamah comes,
Ayrıca, "Kıyamet gelene kadar,
you can go with the ?”. Otherwise, there’s no need.
şeriat ile gidebilirsiniz" dedi. Aksi takdirde,
All these things, he has said It.
buna gerek yok. Bütün bunları o söyledi.
And it’s very important that Islamic world should now take to something like that.
Ve İslam dünyasının şimdi böyle bir şeye yönelmesi çok önemli.
Because the way things are going on, even in Russia,
Çünkü işler bu şekilde giderse, Rusya'da bile
there’s a big fight going on, so many people getting killed for nothing at all!
büyük bir savaş var, pek çok insan yok yere öldürülüyor!
Afghanistan also, such a lot of people are getting killed.
Afganistan'da da pek çok insan öldürülüyor.
We met the Minister of Afghanistan who came to see us.
Bizi ziyarete gelen Afganistan Bakanı ile görüştük.
And he said, “We want peace in Afghanistan. How to have peace?”
O da, Afganistan' da barış istiyoruz. Barış nasıl sağlanabilir?" dedi.
I said, “You spread Sahaja Yoga”.
Ben de, "siz Sahaja Yoga'yı yayın" dedim.
We want peace, he said, “So many people are killing:
Barış istiyoruz, dedi, "Çok fazla insan öldürülüyor:
there are rebels, there are this thing”.
isyancılar var, şu şey var..."
Afghanis, those whom I’ve met are really wonderful people.
Afganlar, tanıştığım Afganlar gerçekten harika insanlar.
They were not political or anything. They didn’t have political problems, nothing.
Politik ya da başka bir şey değillerdi. Siyasi sorunları yoktu, hiçbir şey yoktu.
They were just talking about this and then one of the lady had some problem.
Sadece bunun hakkında konuşuyorlardı ve sonra kadınlardan birinin bir sorunu vardı.
So, she came and she said, “I trust you all the way. I came from Kabul”.
Geldi ve "Siz bana tamamen güvenebilirsiniz. Ben Kabil'den geldim" dedi.
She had some problem, I cured her.
Bir sorunu vardı, onu iyileştirdim.
And I was surprised, I mean, she was just talking about,
Ve şaşırdım, yani, o sadece şöyle diyordu:
“This is what it is, we have we have been watering and all that”.
"Durum şu, biz sulama yapıyoruz ve tüm bunlar..."
Afghanis people say like this. There are people all over the world like that.
Afganlar böyle diyorlar. Dünyanın her yerinde böyle insanlar var.
And Afghanis, I mean, I can say that it’s not easy to penetrate into that area.
Ve Afganlar, yani, o bölgeye girmek kolay değil diyebilirim.
It’s so far fetch.
Çok uzak.
They met me in Russia.
Benimle Rusya'da tanıştılar.
It’s all working out so well.
Her şey çok iyi gidiyor.
Sahaja Yogi: Mother sorry. Mother, sorry, I did not understand.
Sahaja Yogi: Anne, özür dilerim, anlayamadım.
Shri Mataji: No? I’m sorry, I thought you understood.
Shri Mataji: Hayır mı? Özür dilerim, anladığını sanmıştım.
Sahaja Yogi: We’ll [unclear] after this.
Sahaja Yogi: Bundan sonra [belirsiz] yapacağız.
Shri Mataji: You’d better tell them.
Shri Mataji: Onlara söylesen iyi olur.
Sahaja Yogini: Tell him.
Sahaja Yogini: Ona söyle.
Shri Mataji: Ah! [Laughter] I was talking that side.
Shri Mataji: Ah! [Kahkaha] Ben o tarafta konuşuyordum.
Sahaja Yogi: This is recorded, so we can show it to them after this.
Sahaja Yogi: Bu kaydediliyor, bu yüzden ... bundan sonra onlara gösterebiliriz.
Shri Mataji: All right. And then you can translate, yes. Good idea.
Shri Mataji: Tamam. Ve sonra... tercüme edebilirsiniz, evet. İyi fikir.
Sahaja Yogi: This is audio, so yes.
Sahaja Yogi: Bu ses kaydı, evet.
Shri Mataji:
Shri Mataji: Sanırım Türkçe,
I think Turkish is the language I can learn the fastest,
Urduca'ya çok yakın olduğu için
because so much near Urdu.
en hızlı öğrenebileceğim dil.
So much near Urdu. Many words are Urdu words which we use in India.
Urduca'ya çok yakın. Hindistan'da kullandığımız birçok kelime, Urduca kelimeler.
Sahaja Yogini: In Sanskrit, do you mean?
Sahaja Yogini: Sanskritçe mi demek istiyorsunuz?
Shri Mataji: I’ll pick it up in no time.
Shri Mataji: Hemen öğrenirim.
Sahaja Yogini: Can I ask you something?
Sahaja Yogini: Bir şey sorabilir misiniz?
They told me that they saw my name in Sanskrit. My name is Gaiye.
Bana Sanskritçe'de adımı gördüklerini söylediler. Adım Gaye.
What?
Ne?
Sahaja Yogini: Gaiye.
Sahaja Yogini: Gaye.
Shri Mataji: Gaie.
Shri Mataji: Gaye.
Sahaja Yogi: Gaiye. Gaiye.
Sahaja Yogi: Gaye. Gaye.
Shri Mataji: G-A-I
Shri Mataji: G-A-I
Sahaja Yogini: Y-E.
Sahaja Yogini: Y-E.
Shri Mataji: GAIYE. So, you want to know what?
Shri Mataji: GAIYE. Siz ne bilmek istiyorsunuz?
Sahaja Yogini: [Cut]…
Sahaja Yogini: [Kesinti] Sanskritçe.
Sanskrit. They saw it in one of the Sanskrit songs.
Sanskritçe şarkılardan birinde görmüşler.
Sahaja Yogini: She would like to know the meaning of “Gaiye”.
Sahaja Yogini: "Gaye"nin anlamını bilmek istiyor.
Sahaja Yogi: ‘Muslim aliyo gaye’
Sahaja Yogi: "Muslim aliyo gaye"
Shri Mataji: Ah! ‘Gaye’ means ‘you sing the song’. ‘Ga’ comes for singing is for singing, ‘ga’.
Shri Mataji: Ah! "Gaye" "siz şarkıyı söyleyin" anlamına gelir. "Ga" şarkı söylemek için kullanılır, "ga".
It’s for singing, ‘gaye’. it’s an Urdu word ‘gaye’.
Şarkı söylemek için, "gaye". Bu Urduca bir kelime, "gaye".
If I say ‘gaye’ means ‘you please sing’.
Eğer Ben "gaye" dersem, "siz lütfen şarkı söyleyin" anlamına gelir.
But it could be, there was a very well-known lady,
Ama şöyle de olabilir, çok tanınmış bir hanımefendi vardı
and also we have within us one of the channels called as Gayatri Channel.
ve ayrıca içimizde Gayatri Kanalı adında bir kanal var.
Gayatri, it’s a very subtle channel to invoke the five elements.
Gayatri, beş elementi uyandırmak için çok süptil bir kanaldır.
That’s called as Gayatri.
Buna Gayatri denir.
Sahaja Yogi: ‘Gaye’ means the aim or the scope. Is there a word in [Urdu language]? [Cut]
Sahaja Yogi: "Gaye" amaç veya kapsam anlamına gelir.
Shri Mataji: Ah, yes, Urdu. If you say ‘gaye’, means ‘please sing’.
[Urdu] dilinde böyle bir kelime var mı? [Kesinti] Shri Mataji: Ah, evet, Urduca. "Gaye" derseniz, "lütfen şarkı söyle" anlamına gelir.
But what do you say to the sea here? Sea?
Ama burada denize ne dersiniz? Deniz?
Sahaja Yogini: Sea is the niece.
Sahaja Yogini: Deniz, demek.
Shri Mataji: Hum?
Shri Mataji: Hum?
Sahaja Yogini: The niece.
Sahaja Yogini: deniz.
Shri Mataji: No, no. Something else you told me.
Shri Mataji: Hayır, hayır. Bana başka bir şey söylemiştin.
Sahaja Yogini: Sea is the niece.
Sahaja Yogini: Deniz, demektir.
Shri Mataji: ‘Samundan’ you said?
Shri Mataji: "Samundan" mı demiştin?
Something as some word, just like a Sanskrit or Urdu word. Daria.
Sanskritçe veya Urduca bir kelime gibi bir şey. Derya.
Sahaja Yogini: Ah, that’s right.
Sahaja Yogini: Ah, doğru.
Sahaja Yogi: Daria, it’s the ocean ocean.
Sahaja Yogi: Derya, okyanus demek. (Farsça Darya kelimesinden gelir, deniz, büyük nehir anlamlarına gelir)
Shri Mataji: Ocean. Daria is ocean in Urdu also. Daria.
Shri Mataji: Okyanus. Derya, Urduca'da da okyanus demek. Derya.
I’ll pick it up in no time. I’m sure,
Hemen öğrenirim. Eminim,
Turkish language. [Laughter]
Türkçe'de de vardır. Kahkaha]
Even, surprisingly, there are so many words in Russian language.
Hatta, şaşırtıcı bir şekilde, Rusça'da çok fazla kelime var.
It’s very surprising that there’s something what you call [unclear]
Çok şaşırtıcı ki,
that only the Maharashtra from where I come, Bombay,
Benim geldiğim yer olan Maharashtra' da, Bombay 'da,
they say and Russians say and Chinese ‘tse’.
Ruslar ve Çinliler "tse" diyorlar.
Nowhere in the world they use ‘tse’. Mao Zedong is Mao Tsedong, ‘tse’.
Dünyanın hiçbir yerinde "tse" kullanmıyorlar. Mao Zedong, Mao Tsedong, "tse".
So, the Chinese were surprised how I could say ‘tse’
Yani, Çinliler, hiç kimse
because nobody can say ‘tse’. [Laughter]
"tse" diyemediği için
And
benim "tse" diyebilmeme şaşırdılar.
this is something surprising that only in these three countries only this word ‘tse’ is there.
[Gülüşmeler] Ve bu şaşırtıcı bir şey, sadece bu üç ülkede "tse" kelimesi var.
But Sanskrit is in Chinese and in Russian, full of it,
Ama Sanskritçe Çince'de ve Rusça'da var, her yerde var,
completely Sanskrit. Though little derivations are there.
tamamen Sanskritçe. Ancak küçük türevler de vardır.
Because you see, Sanskrit and
Çünkü Sanskritçe ve Latince
we can say Latin [cut] of one mother language.
[kesinti] tek bir ana dilin türevleridir.
Sanskrit means the one which was made holy.
Sanskritçe, kutsal hale getirilmiş olan anlamına gelir.
So, that’s how the one word- Sanskrit started and then the Latin was for the people
İşte böylece tek bir kelime olan Sanskritçe ortaya çıktı ve sonra Latince,
who didn’t want to use very - because Sanskrit is a difficult language.
Sanskritçe'yi kullanmak istemeyenler için ortaya çıktı, çünkü Sanskritçe zor bir dildir.
So, they used Latin.
Bu yüzden onlar Latince'yi kullandılar.
Like this, two languages were good.
Böylece iki dil de iyiydi.
But sometimes these derivations go so far,
Ama bazen bu türevler o kadar ileri gider ki,
that the meaning say, of something is in one language you say a glass’.
bir şeyin anlamı, bir dilde "cam" derken,
So, the meaning of the same word in
başka bir dilde bu
another language could be ‘table’. but the words are there.
"masa" olabilir, ama kelimeler oradadır.
Sahaja Yogi: Are the same. We call Latin language Indo-Aryan language.
Sahaja Yogi: Aynı. Latince'yi Hint-Aryan dili olarak adlandırıyoruz.
We think it comes from Sanskrit language.
Sanskritçeden geldiğini düşünüyoruz.
Shri Mataji: Aryan, yes. Aryan, yes.
Shri Mataji: Aryan, evet. Aryan, evet.
So the Aryans had two languages: one was the Sanskrit and another one was Latin.
Aryanlar iki dil konuşuyordu: biri Sanskrit, diğeri Latince.
But it is said that they don’t know how to say, but they say that, in India,
Ama nasıl olduğunu bilmedikleri söyleniyor, ancak Hindistan'da,
they say that Indians Aryans who went down to Norway,
Norveç'e giden Hintli Aryanlar'ın
because we have a book where they describe that this language was made Sanskrit
bu dili Sanskritçe'ye dönüştürdükleri söyleniyor,
in a place where a constellation called ‘Ramni’ [unsure] is at right angles.
çünkü bu dili "Ramni" adlı bir takımyıldızın [belirsiz] adlı bir takımyıldızının bulunduğu yerde
That’s the place in Norway. So, it was made Sanskrit in Norway by the Indians.
Sanskritçe'ye dönüştürüldüğünü anlatıyor. Bu yer Norveç'te. Yani, Sanskritçe Norveç'te Hintliler tarafından oluşturuldu.
The Viking people perhaps you mean?
Viking halkını mı kastediyorsunuz?
I beg your pardon?
Anlamadım?
Viking, Viking people, in Norway, are they?
Vikingler, Viking halkı, Norveç'te mi?
Shri Mataji: Vikings? Yes.
Shri Mataji: Vikingler mi?
I don’t know if Vikings are but we had we had our ships
Evet. Vikinglerin... ama bizde de
like that built in India long time back, same style.
uzun zaman önce Hindistan'da aynı tarzda gemilerimiz vardı.
The bulbous bows and thing coming out. Sometimes it used to be
Şişkin pruvaları ve dışarı çıkan kısımları vardı.
like a peacock or something.
Bazen tavus kuşu gibi olurdu.
It was like that in India long time back, about thousand,
Uzun zaman önce, yaklaşık bin,
say, 8,000 years back or so, when Shri Rama lived, at that time.
diyelim ki 8.000 yıl önce, Shri Rama'nın yaşadığı dönemde Hindistan'da böyleydi.
So, there we have been always something, there has been a rapport going on
Yani, orada her zaman bir şey vardı,
thousands of years back of which we are not aware historically.
binlerce yıl önce tarihsel olarak farkında olmadığımız bir ilişki vardı.
But certain things you discover and you are quite surprised.
Ama bazı şeyleri keşfettiğinizde oldukça şaşırıyorsunuz.
Like, I went to Colombia, now where is Colombia, Bogota, if you have to go, you see,
Mesela, Kolombiya'ya gittim, Kolombiya nerede, Bogota, oraya siz gitmek zorunda kalırsanız,
the height is so much that you feel little giddy when the plane takes you out there.
yükseklik o kadar fazla ki, uçak sizi oraya götürdüğünde biraz başınız dönüyor.
And in Colombia, it was very surprising that I asked them,
Kolombiya'da, onlara
“Why the emblem of the Navy is a condor? Is a Garuda?”
"Neden Donanmanın amblemi bir kondor? (Tepeli akbaba) Bu Garuda mı?" diye sormam çok şaşırtıcıydı.
So, they said that, “You see, our forefathers told us”,
Onlar da "Bakın, atalarımız bizlere söyledi,
it’s only in Colombia you find people, and Peru, their original Aboriginal people.
sadece Kolombiya'da ve Peru'da, orijinal Aborjin halkını bulabilirsiniz" dediler.
“They told us that there was a god called Vishnu who came on a condor”.
Vishnu adında bir Tanrının kondorun üzerinde geldiğini söylediler.
Both of us, myself and my husband, were surprised.
Hem ben hem de kocam çok şaşırdık.
And from where did he come? He came from Bharat.
Peki nereden geldi? Bharat'tan geldi.
India’s first name was Bharat.
Hindistan'ın ilk adı Bharat'tı.
And in the museum, the fellow told me the same.
Müzede de aynı şeyi söylediler.
So, there was some sort of a big rapport once upon a time.
Yani, bir zamanlar büyük bir bağ vardı.
now, Finland
Şimdi Finlandiya'da,
is so far away.
Finlandiya çok uzak.
And in Finland, I asked the lady, I said,
Finlandiya'da bir bayana sordum,
“What do they call for sugar?” She said, “Sokeria”.
"Şekere ne denir?" diye. O da "Sokeria" dedi.
It’s Sanskrit, absolute Sanskrit word for sugar. What do you call for sugar here?
Bu Sanskritçe, şeker için kullanılan tam bir Sanskritçe kelime. Burada şekere siz ne diyorsunuz?
Sahaja Yogi: Sheker
Sahaja Yogi: Şeker
Shri Mataji: Sheker. From the same, from the same, about the same.
Shri Mataji: Sakar. Aynı kelimeden, aynı kelimeden, yaklaşık olarak aynı.
But in Maharashtra, it is called as ‘saka’ and also in Russian ‘saka’. Exactly ‘saka’.
Ama Maharashtra'da "saka" deniyor ve Rusçada da "saka". Tam olarak "saka".
But the word must be the original Adi Shankara from where,
Ama bu kelime,
all these words have come.
tüm bu kelimelerin geldiği yer olan orijinal Adi Shankara olmalı.
[Unclear conversation about sugar]
[Şeker hakkında net olmayan konuşma]
So, the mixture of Arabic and Persian,
Yani, Arapça ve Farsça,
Latin and Sanskrit. All of them are combinations.
Latince ve Sanskritçe'nin karışımı. Hepsi kombinasyonlar.
Sahaja Yogini: I heard that Sanskrit is the mother of other languages.
Sahaja Yogini: Sanskritçe'nin diğer dillerin anası olduğunu duydum.
I don’t know.
Bilmiyorum.
Shri Mataji: Quite a lot, yes, quite a lot, quite a lot, no doubt about it.
Shri Mataji: Evet, oldukça fazla, oldukça fazla, hiç şüphesiz.
Like in Arabic, you call
Arapça'da olduğu gibi,
it, ‘Kulka kili’ [unsure]; ‘Kulka kili’ for the lock
kilit ve anahtar için "Kulka kiled" [emin değil] diyorsunuz. "Kulka kiled" kilit ve anahtar için.
and key. ‘Kulka kili’ you say. ‘Kuluk kili’ you say in Arabic language.
"Kulka kili" siz diyorsunuz. Arapça'da "Kuluk kili" diyorsunuz.
Sahaja Yogini: In Arabic language, I don’t know.
Sahaja Yogini: Arapça'da, bilmiyorum.
Shri Mataji: They say “Kuluk kili” and that is in Marathi also,
Shri Mataji: "Kuluk" kili diyorlar ve bu Marathi'de de var,
we say “Kuluk” and “kili”. In Marathi.
biz "Kuluk" ve "kiled" diyoruz. Marathi'de.
My father was a scholar of Arabic language and he translated Quran into Hindi. [Unsure]
Babam Arapça bilginiydi ve Kuran'ı Hintçeye çevirdi. [Emin değilim]
Sahaja
Sahaja Yogini: Babam
is a well [unclear sentences].
iyi bir [belirsiz cümleler].
Sahaja Yogini: The manager would like to come and greet
Sahaja Yogini: Müdür gelip
you, is it possible for you?
sizi selamlamak istiyor, sizin için mümkün mü?
Shri Mataji: We have had a Diwali puja. [Laughter]
Shri Mataji: Diwali puja yaptık. [Kahkaha]
Very nice, wonderful Diwali puja.
Çok güzel, harika bir Diwali puja.
They put all the lights and they
Tüm ışıkları yaktılar ve
had lots of these fireworks. Such nice fireworks!
çok sayıda havai fişek attılar. Ne güzel havai fişekler!
Sahaja Yogini: She is Cirilla. Cirilla.
Sahaja Yogini: Bu Cirilla. Cirilla.
Sahaja Yogini: He is the manager of the airport.
Sahaja Yogini: O havaalanının müdürü.
Shri Mataji: Thank you.
Shri Mataji: Teşekkür ederim.
Man: Thank you very much.
Adam: Çok teşekkür ederim.
Sahaja Yogini:
Sahaja Yogini: Sizinle tanıştığı için
He’s very happy to meet you and also he’s very happy to see you in Turkey
çok mutlu ve sizi Türkiye'de
again.
tekrar gördüğü için de çok mutlu.
And while we are waiting for you, we just talk about Sahaja Yoga and yourself
Sizi beklerken, Sahaja Yoga ve sizin hakkınızda konuştuk
and he’s too much interested about this subject that he’s going to join our program.
ve o bu konuya o kadar ilgi duydu ki, programımıza katılmaya karar verdi.
Shri Mataji: Really? Good, very good. Very kind, thank you very much. Thank you.
Shri Mataji: Gerçekten mi? Çok iyi, çok iyi. Çok naziksiniz, çok teşekkür ederim. Teşekkür ederim.
It’s such a nice uh atmosphere. This kind of a freedom [unclear]
Çok güzel bir atmosfer. Bu tür bir özgürlük [belirsiz]
this sense of freedom to get to Sahaja Yoga.
Sahaja Yoga'ya ulaşmak için bu özgürlük hissi.
Very open people I’ve met, very open. Very open.
Tanıştığım insanlar çok açık, çok açık. Çok açık.
But you don’t find this in other countries so called free.
Ama bunu diğer sözde özgür olan ülkelerde bulamazsınız.
You don’t find.
Bulamazsınız.
There so many other things in their heads, I cannot understand why they are like mad people.
Kafalarında o kadar çok şey var ki, neden deli gibi olduklarını anlayamıyorum.
Sahaja Yogini: I didn’t say anything about yourself and Sahaja Yoga.
Sahaja Yogini: Kendiniz ve Sahaja Yoga hakkında hiçbir şey söylemedim.
He asked me the questions all the time. [Laughter]
Bana sürekli sorular sordu. [Gülüşmeler]
Shri Mataji: He must be a seeker, isn’t it? He must be a seeker of truth.
Shri Mataji: O bir arayan olmalı, değil mi? O bir hakikat arayıcısı olmalı.
Sahaja Yogini: I don’t know.
Sahaja Yogini: Bilmiyorum.
Shri Mataji: But this is, I don’t understand,
Shri Mataji: Ama bunu anlamıyorum,
that certain countries are so much full of seekers.
bazı ülkeler neden bu kadar çok arayan ile dolu?
Actually, I mean,
Aslında, Yani, sanki bir şey arıyorlarmış gibi.
as if they are seeking something. You just go there and you find them.
Siz oraya gidiyorsunuz ve onları buluyorsunuz.
And some country you break your head, you break- all your knowledge to them is zero.
Bazı ülkelerde ise kafanızı kırıyorsunuz, tüm bilginiz onlara göre sıfır.
It’s something surprising.
Bu şaşırtıcı bir şey.
Sahaja Yogini: It must be because they are still traditional.
Sahaja Yogini: Bunun nedeni, onların hala geleneksel olmaları olmalı.
Shri Mataji: With their freedom.
Shri Mataji: Özgürlükleriyle.
Sahaja Yogini: Yes.
Sahaja Yogini: Evet.
Shri Mataji: Conditioned by their so-called too much freedom.
Shri Mataji: Sözde aşırı özgürlükleriyle şartlandırılmışlar.
“What’s wrong?” You see, you tell them, they say, “What’s wrong?”
"Bunda ne var ki?" Onlara söylüyorsunuz, onlar da "Ne var ki?" diyorlar.
It’s terrible.
Bu korkunç bir şey.
[28:10 BETTER SOUND]
[28:10 DAHA İYİ SES]
Shri Mataji: I’m sorry, I have to talk this side and you are on this side.
Shri Mataji: Üzgünüm, bu tarafta konuşmam gerekiyor ve siz bu taraftasınız.
Sahaja Yogi: Any side is OK Shri Mataji. [Laughter]
Sahaja Yogi: Her iki taraf da olur Shri Mataji. [Kahkaha]
Shri Mataji: The whole video team wanted to come really.
Shri Mataji: Tüm video ekibi gerçekten gelmek istedi.
I said, No, it’s all right now. Don’t trouble them too much.
Ben de "Hayır, şimdi sorun yok" dedim. Onları çok fazla rahatsız etmeyin.
How much time does it take from here to Bombay?
Buradan Bombay ne kadar sürer?
Sahaja Yogini: It must be 3 hours, 4 hours.
Sahaja Yogini: 3 saat, 4 saat sürer.
Shri Mataji: 4 hours.
Shri Mataji: 4 saat.
Sahaja Yogini: Yes. [Unclear]
Sahaja Yogini: Evet. [Anlaşılmıyor]
Sahaja
Sahaja Yogi: Hayır, hayır.
Yogi: No, no. My wife went to India Tour to New Delhi.
Eşim Hindistan Turu ile Yeni Delhi'ye gitti.
And she left at 10:05 in the evening and she was arriving at 7:35 in New Delhi.
Akşam 10:05'te yola çıktı ve 7:35'te Yeni Delhi'ye vardı.
Shri Mataji: New Delhi, that’s far away, Bombay is closer.
Shri Mataji: Yeni Delhi çok uzak, Bombay daha yakın.
Sahaja Yogini: A local time you mean or?
Sahaja Yogini: Yerel saat mi demek istiyorsunuz?
Sahaja Yogi: Closer, yes.
Sahaja Yogi: Daha yakın, evet.
Shri Mataji: Bombay is much closer.
Shri Mataji: Bombay çok daha yakın.
Shri Mataji: Yes.
Shri Mataji: Evet.
Sahaja Yogini: Local time.
Sahaja Yogini: Yerel saat.
Shri Mataji: I think Bombay would be nearer because
Shri Mataji: Bombay daha yakın olur diye düşünüyorum,
you take one and a half hour to go to Deli from Bombay.
çünkü Bombay'dan Delhi'ye gitmek bir buçuk saat sürüyor.
Sahaja Yogini: And from Italy, here, it’s for 3 hours or 2 hours and a half.
Sahaja Yogini: Ve İtalya'dan buraya gelmek 3 saat ya da 2 buçuk saat sürüyor.
Shri Mataji: It’s very close.
Shri Mataji: Çok yakın.
Sahaja Yogini: From here to Bombay how much?
Sahaja Yogini: Buradan Bombay'a ne kadar?
Akbar: 8 hours.
Akbar: 8 saat.
Sahaja Yogini: So, it’s about 6 hours. Five or six hours yes.
Sahaja Yogini: Yani, yaklaşık 6 saat. Beş ya da altı saat, evet.
Shri Mataji: But you don’t go via- that’s what I was saying,
Shri Mataji: Ama oradan gitmiyorsunuz, Ben de bunu söylüyordum,
if they go to Istanbul, it would be easier.
İstanbul'a giderlerse daha kolay olur.
I was telling them, “You go via Istanbul “. Because I don’t know how they go normally.
Onlara "siz İstanbul üzerinden gidin" diyordum.
Akbar: They go- I don’t know Shri Mataji. Sometimes through Kuwait or through Egypt.
Çünkü normalde nasıl gittiniz bilmiyorum. Akbar: Gidiyorlar, bilmiyorum Shri Mataji. Bazen Kuveyt üzerinden, bazen Mısır üzerinden.
Shri Mataji:
Shri Mataji: İşte bu yüzden.
That’s why. You see, if you go via the north side, then to come to Bombay is much more.
Görüyorsunuz, kuzey tarafından giderseniz, Bombay'a gelmek çok daha zor olur.
But if you go directly from Istanbul it’s - because this is also in the South and Bombay
Ama İstanbul'dan direkt giderseniz
also in the South, so it’s quite close.
bu da güneyde ve Bombay da güneyde olduğu için oldukça yakındır.
I was looking at the map today to find out an easier way.
Bugün haritaya bakıyordum, daha kolay bir yol bulmak için.
So, they are coming now and Russians were saying that,
Şimdi geliyorlar ve Ruslar,
“All our, this thing is booked, we don’t how we’ll go to there”.
"Bizimki, bu rezerve edildi, oraya nasıl gideceğiz bilmiyoruz' diyorlardı.
So, then I found out a way to come here from Tabriz.
Sonra Tebriz'den buraya gelmenin bir yolunu buldum.
They have to go to Tabriz, Ryad, Bombay, it’s straight.
Tebriz'e, Riyad'a, Bombay'a gitmeleri gerekiyor, bu yol daha kısa.
But otherwise, they would go to Delhi from the north from Tashkent,
Ama aksi takdirde, kuzeyden Taşkent'ten Delhi'ye,
Delhi then to Bombay. It’s too much. Yes.
oradan da Bombay'a giderlerdi. Bu çok fazla. Evet.
Moscow is, this way, much easier.
Moskova bu şekilde çok daha kolay.
Sahaja Yogini:
Sahaja Yogini: Anne, Türkiye ile ilgili son sözlerinizi
Mother, would you let me translate your last word regarding Turkey to my friends?
arkadaşlarıma tercüme etmeme izin verir misiniz?
Shri Mataji: All right, please.
Shri Mataji: Tamam, lütfen.
Shri Mataji: There
Shri Mataji: Türkiye ile ilgili bir şey olmalı,
must be something about Turkey, I should say, that there are so many seekers.
diyebilirim ki, çok fazla arayan var.
There must be something, you must find out.
Bir şey olmalı, bunu bulmalısınız.
Maybe there have been some great Saints living here.
Belki burada yaşayan, burada bazı büyük azizler yaşamış olabilir.
Do you think that’s the reasons? There have been lots of saints living in Turkey.
Sence nedeni bu mu? Türkiye'de birçok aziz yaşamıştır.
Kahlil Gibran was here in Turkey? Kahlil Gibran, he’s from Lebanon. He was a saint.
Halil Gibran Türkiye'de mi yaşamıştı? Halil Gibran, Lübnanlıdır. O bir azizdi.
Or Sufi people?
Ya da Sufiler?
Sahaja Yogi: Sufi people, yes. [Unclear]
Sahaja Yogi: Sufiler, evet. [Anlaşılmıyor]
Shri Mataji:
Shri Mataji: Aynen öyle.
Sahaja Yogi:
Sahaja Yogi: Çok var.
There are many. Dervish.
Dervişler.
Shri Mataji: Dervish.
Shri Mataji: Dervişler.
Sahaja Yogini: And though they [unclear] they are close to Sahaja Yoga.
Sahaja Yogini: Ve onlar [anlaşılmıyor] Sahaja Yoga'ya yakındırlar.
Shri Mataji: Yes?
Shri Mataji: Evet?
Sahaja Yogini: Yes.
Sahaja Yogini: Evet.
Shri Mataji: There is
Shri Mataji: Bir şey var.
something.
Sahaja Yogini: Ve sonra Meryem Ana...
Sahaja Yogini: And then the Virgin Mary was born in Ephesus which is Turkey.
Türkiye'nin Efes şehrinde doğdu.
Shri Mataji: Hum?
Shri Mataji: Ha?
Sahaja Yogini: The Virgin Mary was born in Ephesus which is Turkey also.
Sahaja Yogini: Meryem Ana da Türkiye'nin Efes şehrinde doğdu.
It’s near here.
Buraya yakın.
Sahaja Yogi: Ephesus in West Turkey. Her grave is also there.
Sahaja Yogi: Batı Türkiye 'deki Efes. Mezarı da orada.
Sahaja Yogini: Garve?
Sahaja Yogini: Mezar mı?
It’s not a grave because it’s a church.
Mezar değil, çünkü orası bir kilise.
Shri Mataji: Really?
Shri Mataji: Gerçekten mi?
Sahaja Yogini: They said there is the house where she was born.
Sahaja Yogini: Onun doğduğu evin orada olduğunu söylediler.
Shri Mataji: Yes she was born, but at that time it was not Turkey, some other name.
Shri Mataji: Evet, orada doğdu, ama o zamanlar orası Türkiye değildi, başka bir ismi vardı.
Sahaja Yogini: No maybe yes, because the.
Sahaja Yogini: Hayır, belki evet, çünkü...
Shri Mataji: Yes.
Shri Mataji: Evet.
Sahaja Yogi: I think she died there.
Sahaja Yogi: Sanırım orada öldü.
Shri Mataji: She died in- they say she died in Kashmir.
Shri Mataji: O öldü... Onlar onun Keşmir'de öldüğünü söylüyorlar.
She died in Kashmir that’s what they say.
Keşmir'de öldü, öyle diyorlar.
So many people, I don’t know why, at the end of their lives,
Pek çok insan, neden bilmiyorum, hayatlarının sonunda
they say Moses was in Kashmir and so many Jews came to Kashmir.
Musa'nın Keşmir'de olduğunu ve pek çok Yahudi'nin Keşmir'e geldiğini söylüyor.
Like, I don’t know why they came to Kashmir? Maybe it’s a very peaceful place for retirement.
Neden Keşmir'e geldiklerini bilmiyorum. Belki de emeklilik için çok huzurlu bir yer olduğu içindir.
Many Romans came there after
Pek çok Romalı, imparatorluk çöktükten sonra Keşmir'e geldi
they lost their empire. And they died in Kashmir.
Ve Keşmir'de öldüler.
Sahaja Yogini: Because the mountains.
Sahaja Yogini: Dağlar yüzünden.
Shri Mataji: Mountains, it’s a very peaceful, beautiful place.
Shri Mataji: Dağlar, çok huzurlu, güzel bir yer.
So, it was nice meeting you all here. May God bless you.
Hepinizle burada tanışmak çok güzeldi. Tanrı sizi kutsasın.
I hope we get more people tomorrow and day after.
Umarım yarın ve ertesi gün daha fazla sayıda insan gelir.
[Shri Mataji goes out.]
[Shri Mataji dışarı çıkar.]
Shri Mataji:
Shri Mataji: Müslümanların selamlaşma şekli çok daha iyi,
the heart. It’s
içten geliyor.
the heart, you know, they wish.
siz biliyorsunuz, içten dileklerini sunuyorlar.
Man:
Adam: Evet.
Shri
Shri Mataji: Ya da şöyle yapıyorlar.
Mataji: Or they do it like this. [Unclear]
[Anlaşılmıyor]
Sahaja Yogini: And also we greet people like this with
Sahaja Yogini: Biz de insanları bu şekilde,
heart.
içtenlikle selamlıyoruz.
It’s a custom.
Bu bir gelenek.
Shri Mataji: I know, I know. It’s very good instead of shaking hands, you know.
Shri Mataji: Biliyorum, biliyorum. El sıkışmak yerine bu çok iyi, biliyor musunuz?
It’s terrible this shaking hands.
El sıkışmak çok kötü.
Because in Asia, we put both hands together, it’s much better.
Asya'da iki elimizi birleştiririz, bu çok daha iyi.
One hand shaking is very bad. Two hands shaking is better, I think.
Tek elle el sıkışmak çok kötüdür. İki elle el sıkışmak daha iyi, bence.
Guido: It’s good.
Guido: Bu iyi.
Sahaja Yogini: Balance shaking.
Sahaja Yogini: Dengeli el sıkışma.
Shri Mataji: Balance.
Shri Mataji: Dengeli.
Sahaja Yogi: We put it in the heart and really it gives a meaning.
Sahaja Yogi: Bunu kalbe koyarız ve gerçekten bir anlam kazandırır.
Shri Mataji: Really from the heart.
Shri Mataji: Gerçekten kalpten.
[Conversation with few Yogis downstairs.]
[Aşağıda birkaç Yogi ile sohbet.]